Inventory of the Robert Saunders Letters 1829-1867
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Robert Saunders Letters 1829-1867
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2007.109
65.00
This collection consists of 65 letters written by Robert Saunders of Williamsburg, Virginia to his wife Lucy Burwell Saunders (60 letters) and his daughters Lucy Page Saunders (3 letters) and Roberta P. Saunders (2 letters) from 1829-1867.
Saunders, Robert, 1805-1868 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 00/00/2007.
Biographical Note
Robert Saunders was born 25 January 1805 in Williamsburg, Virginia. He attended the College of William and Mary and the University of Virginia. Saunders served as professor of mathematics at William and Mary from 1833 to 1848 and was president of the college 1847-1848. He was a captain in the Confederate States Army, head of Eastern State Hospital, mayor of Willamsburg, vestryman of Bruton Parish and served in the Virginia State Senate. Saunders married Lucy Burwell Page in 1828 and had, among other children, Roberta Saunders and Robert Page Saunders. He died 11 September 1868. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki:
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 65 letters written by Robert Saunders of Williamsburg, Virginia to his wife Lucy Burwell Saunders (60 letters) and his daughters Lucy Page Saunders (3 letters) and Roberta P. Saunders (2 letters) from 1829-1867.
Arrangement of Materials
The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
College of William and Mary--Faculty and Staff
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Topical Term:
College of William and Mary--Alumni and Alumnae.; College of William and Mary--Presidents.; Confederate States of America. War Dept.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--19th century.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- (1)
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Hanover c/o Beverley Blair, Richmond, 16 September 1829 (1)
    Lucy is staying with her sister Margaret (called Peggy). Expresses wish that his wife and infant daughter Mariana Barbara are in good health. Reports on the health of his father, her mother, and sister Barbara. Hopes she has received the gift sent by Mr. Botts for Mariana Barbara.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Hanover c/o Beverley Blair, Richmond, 3 October 1829 (1)
    Weather is very warm, concerns over health matters. Looking forward to being reunited with Lucy and Mariana Barbara. The Empie family and Mrs. Peachy are recovering from the sickness.
    News of Williamsburg. Mrs. Browne and family back in Williamsburg. Judge (?) is expected soon. Mr. and Mrs. Campbell have left for Philadelphia. Mrs. Peachy expecting visit from Mrs. Jane Cary and Mrs. Newsum. They are to settle in Tennessee. Mrs. Peachy received letter from Aunt Tucker reporting Mrs. Robertson will visit Aunt Tucker in winter and Mr. and Mrs. Cabell are well. Miss Mary Pryor to marry. The Coles will attend the wedding Eliza Waller is ill, recovering at Dr. Warren's. Mathew Pierce (my old relation) is very ill and not expected to recover. Mrs. Dabney Browne and her daughter have been sick but recovering. Mr. Browne has painted his house and has used bona fide paint, not whitewash. Mr. and Mrs. Edloe arrived in town. He has read the Devereux and liked it very much.
- (2)
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy c/o Richard Anderson Esq. Richmond, 28 September 1832 (2)
    Betsy Kennon our beloved & lovely friend has died due to complications in childbirth. Very upset. Expresses sympathy for Captain Kennon. Suggests Lucy write to him soon. Received the news from Dr. Peachy at the post office. Expresses gratitude that Lucy and the children are well. Encloses $20. Talks of his father's health as being tolerably well. The servants have recovered from their sickness.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Fauquier Springs Hanover, 30 August 1844 (2)
    Happy she and the children are comfortable at Fauquier Springs. Expresses desire to join them, but fears his health won't allow it. Writes of a sickness that has taken place much later than usual. Speaks in unkind terms of the Judge(?). Others at the springs include Mr. Dew, Judge C. & Miss Martha and the boys and Barbara. Expresses love for his daughters Marianna and Lelia. Glad to hear that she has gotten thro' her teething. Mentions the death of Hughella Page.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Warrenton Springs, 11 August 1845 (2)
    Writing after a trip to Washington DC. He mentions cousin Charlotte, Mary Ann, and Peggy. Explains he accomplished more than anticipated in Washington. Had dinner with Commodore Warrington. Attends a reception at White House. Introduced to President James K. Polk, Mrs. Polk and Beau Hickman. Finds Polk to be a very ordinary looking person, of very ordinary manners and Mrs. Polk a lady of fine manner. Spoke to Old Mrs. Madison at reception for a time and then backed out of the presence of Royalty & descended among the common herd.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg, 2 February 1847 (2)
    Went to St. Paul's in Richmond to hear Bishop John Johns preach. Disappointed by the appearance of someone else preaching in place of Johns. John's appointment (as President of the College of William and Mary) is much talked about in Richmond. Would not know what to say to Johns if they met. Is more and more inclined to leave the college after the next course because of the actions of the Visitors. Will see Holmes again in reference to the situation at the college. Lucy is to have Edmund send oysters via Mr. Whitaker.
- (3)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 14 March 1852 (3)
    Sleepy from a boring sermon given by Dr. Jones. Jokingly will seek to make such sermons illegal. Expresses worry about Lelia's cold. Reminds Lucy of the hereditary weakness of the lungs in his family. Gives his impressions of Senate and role in it. Letter has literary references to The Arabian Nights. Went to see Peggy and Mrs. Botts. They have gone to Cambridge. Hasn't seen Marianna.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 28 March 1852 (3)
    Nothing accomplished in the legislature since his absence as he thought. Was to attend an astronomy lecture at the Athenaeum but found it postponed. Spent evening at the home of Gustavus Myers near the Athenaeum. No regrets about missing a gentleman's party at Halyburton's.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 8 April 1852 (3)
    Hastily written letter after long, laborious Senate session. Coming to Williamsburg, Senate business permitting, via Coke's wharf on Saturday.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg, 22 April 1852 (3)
    Met Senator Mc Sweeney of Wheeling on boat to Richmond. Rode in a hack with Senator and Mrs. Deneale. Mrs. Senator Deneale as rough a specimen (he) ever met with. Busy with Senate work. No time to meet with Mrs. Cabell. Mrs. Greene has left Mr. Barton's and has gone to Philadelphia. Invited to take a trip to Baltimore by officers of the Fredericksburg Railroad with other Senators. Will go if he can spare time away from Senate and continue on to Philadelphia to see his friend Robinson and Mrs. G. Supposes the wedding party has returned to Williamsburg and little lady feels sufficiently married. Will call on Mr. and Mrs. Henley, Ms. Henley and John A. Henley staying at the American Hotel. James River flood up to the lower end of Rocketts due to recent heavy rains causing flooding on the Susquehanna and Potomac also.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 25 April 1852 (3)
    Everyone is well except Barbara. Concerned about Lucy nursing her to health alone. Barbara's old friends Patty Wilson, or Mrs. Ware, or Mrs. Wise or Mrs. Larke should help. Should Barbara complain as to the lack of attention, Lucy is to tell her that he has decided the issue. Attended church and complains of sleep inducing sermon by Dr. Jones. He meets Mrs. Stanard and Mrs. Claiborne. Mrs. Stanard offers accommodations during the approaching convention. Will the children come? Where shall they stay? Suggests Lucy not come to Richmond on the steamboat Augusta to Port Walthall and rail to Richmond, rather via steamboat Curtis Peck to Richmond. Talks about present perplexities of the Whigs as to national politics, busy with the Senate. Death of a member of House of Delegates from Prince George County. Not heard from Mr. Greene. Presumes Mr. and Mrs. Stevenson have left Williamsburg. Mr. and Mrs. Peyton Coles are at the Exchange. Jokes of Mrs. Coles nose which seemedunnecessarily long
    Talks of an unsuccessful attempt to visit Mr. and Mrs. Henley.
- (4)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 28 April 1852 (4)
    Mr. Stanard offers invitation of lodging during the upcoming convention and Mrs. Cabell offers to take care of Barbara and Marianna Lelia can stay with Miss Betty Blair. Arrangement details left to Lucy. Busy with ordinary business of Senate. Writing letters to politicians about the upcoming presidential elections. Received a letter from Mrs. Greene. Mentions the death of John Sergant
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 6 May 1852 (4)
    Coming home to Williamsburg with Mrs. Dunbar. Requests that Lucy send the carriage to Coke's wharf to pick him up. Happy that Bob's cold is better.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 31 May 1852 (4)
    Senate holding evening sessions. Has not had time to see anyone. Barbara is at Dr. Cabell's.
    Curious as to the results of the recent elections. Who was elected Sheriff of James City County? Was Bob Shields elected Sheriff of York County? Judge Clayton won by landslide. Sends a $10 check, written as part of the letter, and it is removed. Asks that Mr. Vest cash it for her.
    Virginia legislature to adjourn on the 7th.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 8 June 1852 (4)
    Will be coming home via Coke's wharf. Sally Galt and Lelia Shield traveling with him. Barbara will not be coming down.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg, 31 January 1854 (4)
    Will be arriving on Saturday at King's Mill. Asks that Lucy not meet him there unless it is "perfectly convenient" for her.
- (5)
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 3 January 1860 (5)
    Cold snap in Richmond. Considerable snow, freezing rain. 15 degree temperatures. Affection for his grandchildren Ann, Mary, Georgy and Breckenridge.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 19 February 1860 (5)
    Talks of approaching Party conventions. Believes the Democrats will choose Stephen Douglas as the candidate at the party convention in Charleston.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 3 September 1860 (5)
    Sent hams and shad to Marianna via Ringgold Station. Peggy is well. Mr. Botts returned to White Sulphur Springs, but didn't see Barbara there. Betty Blair to marry W. Mosely of Buckingham County. Dr. Cabell engaged to Miss Peggy, a music teacher. Mrs. Caskie, wife of Congressman John Caskie, a debased drunkard and sister of Marmaduke Johnson died. Rumors she was brutally treated by her husband supported by Dr. Peterkin sermon at funeral.
    Heard Judge Douglas speak on the Capital square and thinks he made a forcible speech. Mr. Botts is going to speak in Pittsylvania later in the month. Hearing that Mr. Gatewood was preaching at St. Paul's, went to worship at St. James. Heard Dr. Peterkin preach for first time. Disappointed. Mr. Minnegerode and Mr. Woodbridge taking water in the mountains. Mr. Eyler returning to summer home in Hampton. Mrs. Semple returned to Brooklyn in better health. Little news from Williamsburg. Mr. Thomas Lindsey's son died, Mr. Bunting is better.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 14 September 1860 (5)
    Hopes to leave Williamsburg and be with the family week after next. Discussion of Bob's school clothes. Wishes Bob to be decently & abundantly furnished, but fine clothes would beout of place at a country school. Glad Bob is keeping a diary.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 6 January 1861 (5)
    Steamboat taking him to Richmond is decorated with flags in his honor. Dr. Cabell is married.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 11 February 1861 (5)
    Unreliability of mail due to the condition of the railroad damaged by heavy rains, snow and winds. Very busy in Richmond. Bob had difficulty leaving Williamsburg by the York River. Went up the James the next day.
    Comments on the state of the Union and the Virginia convention to consider secession.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 27 February 1861 (5)
    Comments about George Washington at Washington's Birthday celebration in Williamsburg. Not enjoying entertaining members of General Assembly on railroad trip.
- (6)
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Taylorville, Hanover County, 12 September 1862 (6)
    Writes of the excessive heat in Williamsburg.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 16 November 1862 (6)
    Suffering from a hurt. Responds to Lucy's concerns. Explains reasons for going to Richmond are to find work to support family. Thankful children are helping out. Never doubted their devotion. Desperate for work. Looking for employment within Confederate government. Not optimistic about his prospects.
- (7)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 6 February 1863 (7)
    Thinks of his granddaughter Lucy Page when he sees a child. Dreads separation from family. Surmises will get accustomed to it. Busy at his office. Shares space with two workers. Call him Professor. Working six hours a day.
    Found room on 3rd St. between Clay and Leigh and board across the street where Williamsburg friends John Hurley Charles Hansford, William Waller and Sydney Smith live. Asks she address letters to the Ballard House. Sent a package via Mr. Joynes. Hopes she received it and likes the calico.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 9 February 1863 (7)
    Asks Lucy write in care of Captain Charles Morris A.Q.M. in the future. Hopes she has received the sewing cotton in his last letter.
    Has taken residence in a boarding house with some Williamsburg friends. Is comfortable considering difficulty of obtaining accommodations and their price. Not accustomed to work. Has not had the opportunity to visit anyone. Hopes to see General Ewell and Minnegerode tomorrow.
    Visited Drewry's Bluff (Fort Darling) to see Major James Semple. Boards and inspects the ironclad CSS Richmond and the batteries on the bluff. Meets Captain Lee, commander of the naval station at the bluff. Points out he is the brother of General (Robert E.) Lee.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 15 February 1863 (7)
    Raining in Richmond and has a cold. Only going between his room and the boarding house. Didn't go to church. Spending time writing letters. Has sent Bob the permission he desires to go to church out of ranks. Daughters are coming to Richmond to see him and stay at Mrs. Clayton's.
    Doesn't see much of other boarders. Has not been out at night except to get oysters. Has seen only Mr. Branch, Mr. Custis and Alfred Shield. Intends to visit acquaintances soon.
    Misses Lucy, the grandchildren. Offers regards to Mr. Wilmer and friends. Writes of the possibility of promotion in his branch of the Treasury. Robert Taylor trying to find a position for him in his department. Not optimistic about his prospects. Mr. Waller has left the department and returned to Williamsburg.
    Writes of little fight between Confederate cavalry and Yankees on road from Williamsburg in James City County.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 19 February 1863 (7)
    Has seen Lelia and Peggy and was comforted by their visit. Sending money to Lucy and asks she to write if she needs more. Received a letter from General Smith. Bob is acting up and he has written Bob not to throw away his only chance for a gentleman's education. Writes of the death of Dr. Cabell's mother and Mr. Hurley.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 27 February 1863 (7)
    Snow, hail and cold in Richmond. One of the worst days that (he) has known for several years. Writes of the disposition of some of the servants. Little Jim is staying with the Wilmer's. Saunders is grateful to Wilmer for keeping him. Asks that Wilmer use his judgment as to letting Jim stay with Old Fortune or place him elsewhere. Does not intend to sell Fanny at this time. She is with Mrs. Hurley. Old acquaintance in his office Lucy inquired about is Mr. Gilliam, of Prince George County, an older man and member of Minnegerode's Episcopal church. Met Mr. Marshall, Kate Edloe's husband. Nothing else to report about Williamsburg. Has not heard from Bob.
- (8)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, at Pittsylvania C.H., 4 March 1863 (8)
    Sending shirts to Lucy for repair via Mr. Johnson. Provides instructions. Weather has been bad, but his cold is gone. Henry Burwell is sick and of some trouble to Lucy and Mr. Wilmer. Hopes Georgy is better. He is clerk in the 2nd Auditor department and doing a good job, but working below his abilities. Chief clerk would like to promote him. Would relish a promotion and cares only for the increased salary it will bring.
    Hears nothing of consequence about Williamsburg except the Yankees have carried the Hofheimer's to Old Point for selling goods in the country.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania CH,, 8 March 1863 (8)
    Encloses a check for $25. Promises to send more. Disturbed that they can't find fresh provisions and fears they will become scarcer. Prices for board are rising. Heavy rains and thunderstorms. Minnegerode received a letter from his daughters. Sending letter by Gilmer or Semple and will try to send some sugar via Gilmer soon. Mentions Georgy, Breck and darling Lucy Page. Offers remembrances to Dr. Martin and the Vists.(?). Mrs. Coleman servants, Bella, Mira and Beverly have run off. Hopes Lucy doesn't communicate that to their servants.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 12 March 1863 (8)
    Sending 10 pounds of sugar, 10 pounds of rice, some paper, spools of cotton, shoestring, and candy for the grandchildren. Encloses a $25 check. Went to see Lizzie Ewell. She wasn't at home. Weather cold and clear expecting snow or hail. I have not heard from Bob, have you?
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 22 March 1863 (8)
    Weather is bad. Has not gone out, not even to church. the devil has been permitted to rule the weather for 6 or 7 weeks. Wrote Bob and received a reply. He had been suffering from diphtheria but has recovered entirely. Treated by Dr. Robert Madison of the Institute who was formerly a student of the first order. Upset that Breck is sick and his hearing is affected.
    Gratified to hear of Col. Martin's promotion and marriage. Has seen Mr. Semple. He would love to visit them, but wants to be firmly established at the Treasury department. Glad the girls can go to their French School.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 26 March 1863 (8)
    Snow storm, nearly 12 inches deep, the deepest in 20 or 30 years. Offices are closed. Sorry to hear that Ann and Mary are sick. Col Randolph Harrison who told him, according to Mr. George Wise, that Lelia was very sick. Has not heard the same from Mr. Wilmer. Assumes Wise is mistaken. John Gilmer to carry a shirt in need of repair next trip. Sending 4 pairs of summer stockings for darling Lucy Page. Cannot get the eggplant seed she requested...but will keep trying. Dr Coleman has resigned, gone to Warrenton NC. Mrs. Tucker intends to return to Williamsburg. John Barlow lost his wife. his family was in New Kent County. Has seen Mr. Morecock and his brother-in-law Captain Taylor.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 29 March 1863 (8)
    Distressed to hear that Ann and Mary are still sick. Sending 5 pounds of sugar, some soda, and a few dough nuts for the darling children and a harmonica for Georgy and Breck and a fan for Lucy via Mr. Wilmer. Not been able to procure the egg plant seed. Reports no news of consequence from Williamsburg. Heard a sermon from Minnegerode and saw Bishop Johns confirm people at St. Paul's. I hope you have heard from Bob.
- (9)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 5 April 1863 (9)
    Mr. Patton. Purchased 31 yards of unbleached cotton (at $1.75/yard) and will send to Mr. Pollack. Has little to do in the afternoon and will be pleased to hunt for articles for them. News from Williamsburg via Mr. W. H. Pierce who has heard it from others. Pierce is afraid to go into Williamsburg since he sells goods secretly. Pierce bought a letter from Mr. Sweeney. Sweeney took 5 mules from the Saunders property. The Yankees stole one, two to Isham for use on the farm, one to Gawian for use on Mrs. Henley's and one to Mrs. Sydney Smith.
    Isham claims slaves that remain in Williamsburg will wait for their masters' return and are unhappy at the treatment of the Yankees. Jacob (Mrs. Tucker's servant) has left for Hampton.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 12 April 1863 (9)
    Received the shirts she sent by Mr. Lefebvre. Will be sending a package back via him to include white cotton for 4 shirts for Bob and a piece of linen. Met Martha Page. Mr. Sheldon had just come up from Gloucester with news that the Yankees had committed more deprivations in that county. Met Mrs. Peachy for the first time since leaving Williamsburg. Presumed that she was unhappy to see him looking well and in health. Heard that General Wise has gone down to Williamsburg and was driving the Yankees south. Presumes that Wise has taken Fort Magruder. Sees Julia Johns. Memminger says he sorry about his position and that he could not find something more worthy. Doubts sincerity of remark. The bread riots were realis war not a bread riot war is merely the pretext for plunder..
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 14 April 1863 (9)
    Diphtheria epidemic. Concerned that Lucy is tired caring for the sick especially the servants who don't know how to attend to each other.
    Sending a plate to Lelia as to replace one of Mrs. Lefebvre's broken at the Rectory. Inventory of what box he has sent. An old towel, shirts, small quantity of Passover bread from Mrs. Heller, a doll for Lucy Page, caps for Georgy and Breck, 31 yards of unbleached cotton (at 1.75/yd), shoestrings, 20lbs sugar, 20 lbs of rice, 6lbs coffee (at $3.50 which is cheap! by a dollar, 1lb green tea, ½ lb black tea and 2 oz of soda, a tin horn for Georgy and a whistle for Breck, candy and $50. Nothing more specific from General Wise at Williamsburg. Minnegerode's son James has a warrant as midshipman.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 26 April 1863 (9)
    Sending a sample of fabric ($5.50/yd). Sent Lelia a box of Beckwith's Pills. Jim and Cyrus have been hired at a tobacco factory. Relieved Wilmer is free of their support. Heard accounts of deprivations of Yankees in Gloucester and of people fleeing.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 3 May 1863 (9)